hey P students let's cover everything
you need for period
9 before we start pronounce the free
speed review sheet you can find the link
in the description below right now look
at period 9 Circle any people events or
vocab things that you don't quite
remember that you know you want to focus
on as we review then as you're confident
that you've mastered these topics you
can check them off and move on to the
next one all right here we go period 9
is one of the shortest units in a push
so you'll likely only see a few
questions on your AP exam you'll never
see period 9 in a DBQ but you're highly
likely to see it in the multiple choice
section Ronald Reagan won the election
of 1980 against Democrat incumbent Jimmy
Carter during his campaign he promised
to implement conservative policies and
reduce government intervention in the
economy the support of groups like the
Moral Majority also helped him win the
election his Economic Policy was known
as ronom and emphasized supply side
economics tax cuts and deregulation the
impact of Reaganomics continues to be
debated while some argue that it
improved economic growth others
criticize Regan nomics for widening the
wealth Gap and increasing the national
debt The Regan Administration was also
criticized for their role in the Iran
Contra affair this event involved the
illegal sale of arms to Iran with the
profits being used to fund
anti-communist rebels in Nicaragua
ultimately Americans questioned how much
Reagan actually knew about these illegal
acts which caused his approval ratings
to drop Reagan's Administration also
focused on National Defense Regan's
policies also helped bring an end to the
Cold War he eased tensions by opening
lines of communication with Soviet
leader Mel gorbachov he also challenged
gorbachov to tear down that wall calling
on him to bring greater freedom and
openness to Eastern Europe Miss Mr
gorbachov teared down this
wall ultimately the Berlin Wall fell on
November 9th 1989 George HW Bush
Reagan's vice president won the
presidential election of 1988 this was
due to Reagan's popularity and his
campaign promise read my lips no new
taxes Bush's presidency included the
Persian Gulf War also known as Desert
Storm the goal of this military
operation was to liberate Kuwait from
Iraq's Invasion and and to protect oil
reserves in the region with the US
leading a coalition of international
forces and achieving its objective with
relatively low casualties the Persian
Gulf War was considered a military
success Bush's presidency also saw the
end of the Cold War with a dissolution
of the Soviet Union in 1991 despite his
foreign policy successes Bush lost his
reelection to Democrat Bill Clinton his
loss was attributed to an economic
recession which forced him to break his
promise on no new taxes and the addition
of third party candidate Ross perau
ultimately Bill Clinton won the election
of 1992 running as a more moderate new
democrat one of Clinton's campaign
promises was lifting the long-standing
ban of gay and lesbian individuals
enlisting in the American armed forces
although his don't ask don't tell Bill
technically fulfilled this promise it
was controversial while it prohibited
discrimination against service men and
women based on their sexual orientation
it also banned individuals who were
openly gay in lesbian from serving in
the military one major policy
achievement of the Clinton
Administration was the NAFTA agreement
between the United States Mexico and
Canada this aimed to reduce trade
barriers and promote economic
cooperation in North America a domestic
success of the Clinton Administration
was the budget reform where he was able
to reduce the federal deficit by
increasing taxes on high inome
individuals while also cutting spending
however most of Clinton's achievements
were overshadowed by his impeachment
proceedings the house brought charges of
perjury and obstruction of justice in
regards to Clinton's testimony about his
affair with intern Monica Lewinsky but
he was acquitted in the Senate
Republican George W bush son of George H
W bush won the presidential election of
2000 this was one of the most contested
presidential elections in American
history which ultimately had to be
decided in the Supreme Court with the
case Bush VOR Bush faced a series of
challenges during his presidency
including the federal response to
Hurricane Katrina and a Severe economic
recession the 2008 economic crisis was
caused by a lack of oversight in the
financial industry including poor
lending practices which led to a housing
crisis this is also known as the Great
Recession one of his most important
pieces of legislation was the No Child
Left Behind Act this set standards for
academic achievement and held schools
more accountable for student performance
but some criticized this policy
especially for it emphasis on
standardized testing but ultimately the
bush presidency was dominated by arise
and terrorism the war on terror started
after the September 11th 2001 attacks by
Al-Qaeda on the World Trade Center which
killed
2,977 Americans This marked a
significant shift in US foreign policy
and national security measures in the
aftermath of 9/11 the US government
passed the USA Patriot Act which
expanded surveillance and law
enforcement powers to combat terrorism
President Bush also created the
department of H and security to better
protect America from future attacks in
following 9/11 President Bush promised
to bring down what he referred to as
aess of evil American forces fought
against terrorism in both Iraq and
Afghanistan operation Iraqi Freedom
focused on removing weapons of mass
destruction from Iraq and bringing down
Saddam Hussein operation during Freedom
focused on ending the Taliban and
Al-Qaeda as well as finding Osama bin
Lan and history was made in 2008 when
Barack Obama became the first
African-American president of the US
during his campaign Obama promised
Healthcare reform this was achieved with
the Affordable Care Act act often
referred to as Obamacare which aimed to
expand Healthcare access to millions of
Americans however conservatives opposed
the law arguing that it represented
government overreach and debated the
constitutionality of individual mandates
one of the major challenges Obama faced
as president was the ongoing economic
crisis as a result of the Great
Recession he implemented a series of
measures including the American Recovery
and reinvestment act which sought to
stabilize the economy create jobs and
prevent similar economic collapses in
the future Obama's presidency also
oversaw the successful operation that
led to the killing of Osama bin Laden
the leader behind the 9/11 terrorist
attacks Obama also fulfilled his
campaign promise to bring the troops
home from Iraq and Afghanistan which
ended the longest wars in American
history America also experienced
significant economic changes during
period 9 globalization reshaped the
world's economy with interdependence
between nations this opened up new
markets for American businesses but it
also increased competition with overseas
manufacturers because of this America
experienced a decline in manufacturing
especially in industrial states which
became known as the rust belt this led
many Americans to leave the industrial
Rust Belt cities and move to the
Suburban Sun Belt region with the influx
of Prior City dwellers into more rural
regions the influence Southern States
had on National politics increased
significantly in period 9 we also see
how technology reshaped America's
society and economy the rise in personal
computers impacted a variety of fields
from business to finance and education
to entertainment this also led to the
creation of the internet which led to
the doom boom online capabilities
contributed to the globalization process
economically but also Al impacted
society and culture with the rise of
cell phones and social media platforms
these new platforms connected people
ideas and businesses across the globe
this period saw a significant shift in
Immigration which also inspired new
immigration policies after 1980 the
largest portion of American immigrants
were coming from Latin America and Asia
Census Data from 2010 revealed that
Asians were the fastest growing
immigrant group in America the number of
Asian immigrants has doubled from 1970
to now and that's attributed to the
Immigration Act of 1965 which lifted
strict quotas on Asian immigrants
significant immigration policies were
passed by several administrations Reagan
approved the immigration reform and
Control Act and Obama signed the DACA
act so what does this look like on exam
day for causation you could be asked
about effects of Reagan's economic
policies specifically Reaganomics
College Board might also ask you about
the causes and effects of globalization
comparison questions might ask about
recent political polarization
specifically for you to compare
conservative and liberal ideologies and
for continuity and change you're likely
to see questions about changes in
foreign policy after the the Cold War so
be ready for multiple choice asking
about America's involvement with the
Middle East from Harry Truman to George
W bush check out the aush ultimate
review packet for more help we've got
timeline study guides and Essay practice
follow the link in the description below
to get a free preview and if you think
this video was helpful like And
subscribe thanks for
watching